<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle vnto the right honorable and christian prince, the Duke of Somerset written vnto him in Latin, awhile after hys deliueraunce out of trouble, by the famous clearke Doctour Peter Martyr, and translated into Englyshe by Thomas Norton.</title>
            <title>Epistle unto the right honorable and christian prince, the Duke of Somerset.</title>
            <author>Vermigli, Pietro Martire, 1499-1562.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B16185</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840955</idno>
  <idno type="VID">176396</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240868330</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 24666</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S105226</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99840955e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B16185)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176396)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 157:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle vnto the right honorable and christian prince, the Duke of Somerset written vnto him in Latin, awhile after hys deliueraunce out of trouble, by the famous clearke Doctour Peter Martyr, and translated into Englyshe by Thomas Norton.</title>
                  <title>Epistle unto the right honorable and christian prince, the Duke of Somerset.</title>
                  <author>Vermigli, Pietro Martire, 1499-1562.</author>
                  <author>Norton, Thomas, 1532-1584.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By N. Hill] for Gualter Lynne, dwellynge on Somers Kaye, by Byllinges gate],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprynted at Londo[n] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno a verbo incarnato. M.D.L. Regni Edwardi sexti. iii. [1550]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC. Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>With a final colophon leaf.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Somerset, Edward Seymour, --  Duke of, 1506?-1552 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176396:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176396:1"/>
            <p> An epistle vnto the right honorable and christian Prince, the Duke of Somerset writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vnto him in Latin, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>none after hys deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce out of trouble, by the famous clearke Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour Peter Martyr, and translated into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyshe by Thomas Norton.</p>
            <p>Anno a verbo incarnato. M.D.L. Regni Edwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di sexti. iii</p>
            <q>Whan I was in trouble, I called vpō the lord, &amp; he hard my voice. <bibl>psal. 120. a Ion. 2. a.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>decorative border</figDesc>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>statue of Justice (left)</figDesc>
                  <head>IVSTITIA</head>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>statue of Prudence (right)</figDesc>
                  <head>PRVDENTIA</head>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal coat of arms of Edward VI (bottom center)</figDesc>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROYT</q>
               </figure>
            </figure>
            <pb facs="tcp:176396:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:176396:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou maye peraduenture thynke it a straūge &amp; mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uellous thīg, moste excellēt Duke, that I am so bolde as nowe to begin to wryte vnto you. It had ben my dewtie to haue done it rather before, when the tē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest had almost drowned you, and we (whiche began to reioyse for the enterprised, but not fullye en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, restorynge of religyon) were in maner ouercome with sorowe and greate heuynes. And par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture it would not haue dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleased you, yf I or any suche as I shoulde haue wryten vnto you. For where tentation dothe abounde, there a frendlye &amp; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian confortynge beynge vsed go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not without his effecte. But I
<pb facs="tcp:176396:3"/> and other of my profession, in that perillous tyme were lytle lesse troubled than you. Yea, I dare say for you, that you youre selfe were of better cheare in the myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the water, than we that stode vpon the shore and behelde your wreck. Wherfore I thought it metest to spēde that tyme in we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge and in prayers, for to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne, bothe preseruacion for you whiche haue done so muche good in religyon, and also a sure staye for the churche, for as muche as it was alredy shaken. And now that you maye haue a testimonye of the ioye, whiche I haue concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by your delyuerance, &amp; of my sorowe past, I thought it best not to let go this occasion, but by this my epistle, suche as it is, with such reuerence as is mete, with suche modestie as becommeth, bothe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyse of your happye lucke, and
<pb facs="tcp:176396:3"/> comforte you touchynge those thynges which haue of late dayes happened vnto you, not withoute the ordinance of almyghtye God. For them that haue ben once vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with greuous myseries, the rē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nātes of myschieffes are wont of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to greue, and make them not a lytle sorye that they were dryuen to suffre that, which they were as lytle worthye of, as they lytle thought that any such thīg should chaunce. As for that whiche I haue taken vpō me, yf I performe it not so well as my wyll is, yet I praye you to take it in good parte, and at the least yet gētlye to accept this token of my harte towarde you. It is set forthe in the histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye of the holy gospel, that the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples were in a ship Christ beyng absente, there rose a mightye storme, the wynde was so sore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynste them, and the waues dyd
<pb facs="tcp:176396:4"/> so well that they had no hope of sauynge their lyues. Then Christ, whiche alwayes at suche tyme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stirreth hym selfe to helpe vs, whē we are in maner brought euen to despeire, aboute the latter ende of the nyght came vnto them. When they sawe him go vpon the water, they were the more afrayde, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they thought that he was a spirite or fantasticall thynge. But when he bade them be of good cheare, Peter (whiche dyd alwai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es beare a burnynge loue towarde Christe) as soone as he hearde him thus speake, sayed. Mayster, yf it be thou, byd me to come vnto the vpon the water. He thoughte hym selfe, yf he were once in hys maysters companie, saffer from the storme, than yf he had kepte hym selfe styll within the defence of the shyppe. When he had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned Iesus commaundemente,
<pb facs="tcp:176396:4"/> he made haste towarde hym vpon the water, and as longe as he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vpon Christe, and cleaued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his worde by faythe, he did wel ynough. But when he loked but a lytle a syde from Christ, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sydered the boysteousnes of the wynde and raginge of the waues, his faythe wauered and he began to synke. Then, the so great daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger dyd thus muche profyt hym, that he loked vp agayne to Christ, and cryed out: Helpe me, o Lorde, els I peryshe. Christ gaue him his hande, whereby he plainly taught, that the daunger that he was in, came not of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> rage, other of wynde or waues, but by the weaknes of hys faythe. For, sayde he, why dyddest thou stumble by reason of thy weake and feble faythe. Whyle I cōsyder this noble historie, good Lorde, I do gather and perceaue many thynges in it that do fytlye
<pb facs="tcp:176396:5"/> agre with your chaunce. For all men do knowe, that to rule a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune weale is as it were to sayle ouer a depe sea, whiche is alwayes tossed with tempestes, and alway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es swelleth with myghtie stormes of wynde. Herein were you, and whan there was almoste no hope of your preseruation, Christe was with you, and suffred you not to peryshe, seynge that you haue so aduaunced his relygion, whiche o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers estemed not to be true, but a spirite, a fantasye, a thyng made to deceaue, and neuer thoughte that your confydence in the gospel of Christ would do you any good. But it hath so helped you that you haue trodē vnder your fete the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge waues and mightie storme. And, sethe we ar men, it was possy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that your faythe, (althoughe by the helpe of God it be feruent,) myght wauer. Therefore, when
<pb facs="tcp:176396:5"/> you consydered your selfe to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moste drowned, I dowbte not that you cryed out. Oh lorde, yf I haue beleued no lies, yf thy gospel be true whiche I haue promoted, yf thy worde hathe not begyled me, saue me this houre that I pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryshe in. Wherfore he to delyuer hys truthe of wholsome and sure faythe frō the despite of scorners, by and by he gaue you his ryghte hande to helpe you, and set you in safetye, so that I doubte not, it hathe bene bothe a great pleasure to all godlye men, and shalbe gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly proffitable vnto you. For thus you do perceaue, not onely by faithe, but also by experience, how sure a staye it is to leane vnto true godlynes. And nowe you haue no nede of any other man to preache vnto you y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> whiche we rede wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the Romanes. Who shall plucke vs from the loue that God
<pb facs="tcp:176396:6"/> beareth towarde vs? shal trouble? shal sorowe? shal persecution? shal hunger? shall nakednes? shall dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? shal the swerde? No. Yea he addeth further, we ouercome in al these thinges throughe him which loueth vs. Surelye (moste noble Duke) greuous thinges in dede haue happened vnto you. Al thīges in maner were stirred vp agaynste you alone. But who ouercame thē in you but Christe? who hath cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med so great a storme raysed vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst you but Christ? The wicked styll loked for you to haue no other chaunce but extremite. But who dyd wrastle for you against presēt death, and destruetion hangynge ouer your head but Christe? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, yf you be wise, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> you thinke no otherwyse. As for al vs that do embrase godlynes, we do confesse with one mouthe with one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, that Christ hath taken your
<pb facs="tcp:176396:6"/> parte: And I doubte not that you your selfe haue boldlye sayd with Paule. If God be on our side, who is against vs. This sure comforte godlye men haue alwayes at hāde in aduersitye. We are Goddes, we do belonge vnto Christ. God hath taken vpon him our defence. They say that they be mightye whiche fight agaīst vs, but what? are they stronger than God? We know and stedfastlye beleue that God is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, who shall ouercome hym that is almyghtye. O wholsome comforte? O sure toure of Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an faithe? O faith buylded not vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on sande but vpon a moste stronge rocke? Pompei in his desperate state coulde not so comforte hym selfe, nor Cicero in his banishemēt, on the laste houre of hys miserable destruction coulde strengthen hys courage being weakened on euery syde, with anye suche comforte. I coulde reherse Brutus, Cato, and
<pb facs="tcp:176396:7"/> many other noble men after y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement of the world, which whyle they wer in state other prosperous or tolerable, semed bothe wyse and valiant men, but when they sawe thē selues brought to the extremite that there was no remedy or helpe, we rede that they other cryed out, Oh neuer was I wyse, or blamed bothe God and men, and knowyng not what to do, now layed y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> faulte vpon destenie, now vpon fortune, nowe vpon falshed of men. Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times desperatli thei would accuse and lay the faulte vpon their owne blinde councelles. And many ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, whiche they had in redynes, they would comforte thē selues w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the abhominable and mischeuous remedye to kyll thē selues. But we, yf we purely agree vnto the gospel do vndoubtedlye beleue, that God our father and Christe is almygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye. Hym we haue put in truste
<pb facs="tcp:176396:7"/> to defende oure cause. Therfore so we do reason with our selues, when we are in any great daūger. They that come againste vs, must prepare them selues to fighte not against mē, but against God. Whō he that striueth agaīst, hurteth not him, but maketh him selfe onely miserable. Therfore God sayd frō heauē to Saul y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> most earnest per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutour of Christians, it is harde for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> to kicke agaynst y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prick. For the prick is not hurte thereby, but it woūdeth the heles y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> do strike at it. Wherfore we must not despeire, we must not disquiet our self with to much care. We muste not go to it with crying, with wepīg, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> stir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rīg vp of troublesome sediciōs, we rest vnder the shadowe of goddes winges, Christe shall care for vs. We are couered with the shelde of Gods mercy. Nothing can happen
<pb facs="tcp:176396:8"/> vnto vs, but it maketh for our pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyt and the glorye of God. Herby am I perswaded to beleue y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> you dyd comfort your selfe in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of your troble, which I know y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> flesh is wont to wrastle against, and bringeth forth these reasons. These comfortes in dede that you speake of ar somwhat worth. But tell me not that in these greuous troubles Christian men do suffre nothinge. I perceaue, I se by expe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rience that they take not awaye our sorowe, our vexations, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we are almoste oppressed are no lesse greuous, our paines wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>with we are sore punished are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge eased by these comfortes. While they are spokē in dede they encourage oure hearte, but that doth profyt nothing, but to fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, &amp; is more hurt by the newe fall than if it had been in one state still. For when a man hath taken a good hert vnto him, if deliuerance
<pb facs="tcp:176396:8"/> do not straight way folow, a grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter heape of mischiefes withoute remedy assaileth a freshe, yea and that so hard, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it whorleth downe with more hedlonge destruction than before. So is the flesh wont to trouble the refreshinges by the gospell and to barke agaynste the heauenlye comfort. But leaste the power of the fleshe make vs lese so greate fruite, we muste consider y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> plentuous and full light of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian doctrine, least while we be to earnestlie moued with those thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which the flesh putteth in our head, we take y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lesse hede to those thinges whiche we ought to loue. What can happen more happie to a christian man than bothe to be &amp; be accōpted the scholer of Christe? what more luckie thing can he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syre, than to reigne for euer w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hys maister? what more to bee wished for, than to obteine euerlasting life with great glory. But these thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb facs="tcp:176396:9"/> are not attayned but by the crosse. The sons of zebede moued by a certayne gredines of honour, set theyr mother to require y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they shuld sit next to Christ in his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome as head &amp; chiefe. To whome he answerd. Can ye drinke of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cup whiche I shall drynke? Can ye be washed with the baptisme wherw<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I shalbe washed? By whiche wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des he plainlye declared y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> all they that wil reigne foreuer, must drinke vp the cuppe of aduersitie. And as many as are trewe suters for the heuenly kingdome must be washed with the baptisme of persecution. Finnallye without circumstances oure maister whome we professe Iesus Christe hathe taughte that none shall bee his disciple, whiche will not willingly take vpon him his crosse, whereupon let him see that he nayle bothe himselfe, hys flesh, and the lustes therof. For the
<pb facs="tcp:176396:9"/> whiche cause also saincte Paule writinge to the Romaines dothe diligently instruct the congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, sayinge: if we suffre with him, we shalbe glorified with him, and he addeth a comfort sayinge that he doth not esteme the troubles of thys worlde to be lyke the glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye whych shalbe declared in vs. And to Timothe he saieth that he bringeth a sure and approued say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge, that if we die together with Christ, we shall liue together with him, &amp; if we suffre together with him we shal reigne with him. And vnto the same man in the first epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle he sayth that all they that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende to liue godlye in Christ Iesu muste suffre persecution. And it is no otherwise mete. For it is no rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>son that we shoulde entre into the inheritance and kingdom an other way, than Christe him selfe entred into it. He obteined the kingdome
<pb facs="tcp:176396:10"/> by obedience, glorye by shame, fre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome from deathe by crosse and deathe. Further it is mete that the meanes and the ende shoulde haue a cōuenient likelhode. Seing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we be called therunto of God our father (whiche we must consy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with our selues now and thē) to be changed into the image and likenes of his sonne our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>su Christ, that euen so as he trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing after he had ouercome deth, and other temptations of this life, entred into euerlastynge life, so it may at length be in vs whiche are accompted his membres, as we se hathe been done alredye in oure head. Therfore it is mete that they which entend to obteine the same kind of reward, shoulde practise y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same kinde of maisteries and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. The which thing the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle of Christ gaue vs warninge of when he sayde. Those whome he
<pb facs="tcp:176396:10"/> hathe foreknowen, he hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted before to be lyke to the image of his sonne. Whereby it appereth how excellent the state of the cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen is. These thinges did God of his owne free will gyue vs before we were, when we loked for no suche thinges: he gaue vs greater thinges than we durste aske, and more than we would haue hoped for. Sainct Paul addeth farther and sayth. Whome he hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted before, them he hathe called, whō he hath called, them he hathe made ryghteous, whome he hathe made ryghteous, them he hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so made glorious. These so many and so great gyftes our most gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle father hath appoynted and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs, not that we shoulde geue place to the frowarde counselles of our fleshe, which other refuseth the crosse, or wyll not suffre it selfe but softlye and pleasauntlye to be
<pb facs="tcp:176396:11"/> nayled vnto it. And howe fonde a thyng is it to turne the crosse to a couche, &amp; the sorowfull gallowes in to a softe fetherbed. Suche thī<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, I saye, were not geuen vs, that we shoulde be afrayed by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersitie, mysfortune, or myserie, &amp; leaue the steppes of Christe, to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe our senses or the iudgement of reason. But when we haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sydered that all these thynges are geuen vs so lyberally of the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefulnes of God, aboue the desert, aboue the worthynes, aboue the strength of oure nature that we be nat vnmyndfull, vnthankfull, fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyshe, as they are, which by folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng the fleshe &amp; cōmodities ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to auoyde aduersities, and so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, that are but shorte and cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue for a tyme, do cruellye robbe them selues of eternall life, and do wickedly forsake the wayes of godlines. Euen as Iob answered
<pb facs="tcp:176396:11"/> his wife, when (in stede of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort whiche she should haue geuen her afflicted husband) she caste hys pure godlines in his teth: euen so oughte we to answere oure fleshe whē it begīneth to be so bold as to rayle and bable against the heauē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye comfortes. Why (sayeth Iob) haste thou spoken as one of the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lysh women? Seing we haue rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued good thinges of the lord, why shuld we not receaue the euel also? O maruailous and incredible sted fastnes of the man of God? Howe circumspectely, how wiselie, howe godly, he answered here? Ther can nothing be immagyned more fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lysh than the flesh, speciallye when it bableth against the word of god It seeth nothing, it regardeth thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges present onlye, it neuer vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standeth that whiche the Apostle preached. We reioyce in trouble, knowing that trouble engendreth
<pb facs="tcp:176396:12"/> sufferaunce, sufferance engendreth profe, profe engendreth hope. So the spirite of God poureth oute it<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selfe, that out of the stormes of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series he may brīg fourth strength whereby we may be able to abide them: and out of this sufferance he bringeth fourth the tryed know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our selues. Wherby we ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selye perceaue, howe fraile we are of our selues, and howe strong we are by the helpe of Christe. By the which knowledge when we haue so proued what is ours and what is Gods, we conceaue in our mind a great boldnes of the help of god For we doubt not that god which hath once layed his hand vnder vs when we were redie to fall, wyll do the same whē other like or har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der danger shall assayle vs. For by the benefites whiche we receaue, the loue of God towarde vs is so farre from being vnknowen, that
<pb facs="tcp:176396:12"/> it poureth it self into euery corner of our hartes. Wherefore there is no longer anye excuse lefte for vs to doubt therof, wherby in vs also is stirred vp a loue toward god, to set more by him, his will and com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundementes than all our owne commodities, profites, desires &amp; purposes. Behold these be the gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uous dammages, these be the los<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, these be the hinderances, these be the euels that godly mē gather of aduersite. Surely seing so plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull fruites, and large profites come to the chosē therby, the wise forseing gentlenes of our almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty father did not il prouide for vs, which hath opened vs the way to heauen through crosse &amp; troubles. For we are led vnto this by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees aforesayd, chiefly to truste to our creatour, and all our affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions moste feruently to leaue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him alone. Therefore (vnles we
<pb facs="tcp:176396:13"/> to folysh as sone as we haue esca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped afflictions &amp; trouble, we muste geue oure heartie thankes to the mercy of god. For in them y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> power of God dothe appere more than in any other thyng. This one thinge in dede doth often greue the chosen of God in afflictions, that they see the vngodly and thē that haue vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly putte away al care of godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to liue ī quiet, to possesse their goods, commodities and honours vnto their lyues ende, whyle they are shaken with most myghty tēp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacions, with sundrye &amp; manyfold engines of the deuell, but they do not consyder, that the deuel is gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ynoughe to them that trouble him not, that whyle he semeth in manner to flatter his, leaste they should forsake him, by this trayne he maye entyse many moe vnto him. A snake hurteth no man that toucheth him not, but yf thou
<pb facs="tcp:176396:13"/> presse him neuer so lytle, strayght waye he riseth vp against the with fearfull hyssinge and armed wyth poyson. A scorpion semeth very gē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and as thoughe he woulde em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brase a man, but touche him neuer so lytle, and he wil turne the daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous sting in his tayle againste the. You (right excellent lord) haue sore hurte the deuell which is both a snake and a scorpion, and ruler of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> darkenes of this world, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore what maruel you if he labour to destroy you? Sureli, if I might se it otherwise chaunce, I would much muse and be dismaide at the contrarye fashion of thynges. He sore suspecteth that he shall not be able to fraye the people of Christe from the gospell, vnles he rage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst you, by whome supersticion is maruelouslye broken, by whom the lyght of godlynes hath geue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallie shined vpō this realme. But
<pb facs="tcp:176396:14"/> comforte your selfe and be strong. His power hath an ende, he cā not passe his bondes. But beware of this one thīg that you nether con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syder nor remembre to ofte, youre olde state, wherin you were before your fall. For as ofte as any suche thought commeth in your minde, the flesh complayneth againe that much goodes is takē away, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which it iudgeth escapīg with life not to be swete, and murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that it were better to haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at once, than to haue recouered a life so broughte out of fashion. But we must not suffre our minde so to be moued with them, but y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it may put away y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mist when it wil &amp; se that w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> taking awaye of great authorities, heapes of honours, &amp; chief orderinge of matters, greate cares are also cut away. You may not learne of me how busy &amp; how painfull a thing it is to rule a com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mune
<pb facs="tcp:176396:14"/> weale w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> counsel &amp; good pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uision. For that you your self haue ben sufficiently taughte by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to knowe. Now at length (as I thinke) you may haue more lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to study godlines and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thinges belonging to god Wherfore I wold haue you thus to thinke, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> you muste nedes haue raunsomed this quietnes and pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sable life, with some losse of those goods, which (I dare say for you) you neuer greatlye passed for, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> commune people do sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly esteme &amp; specially regarde them. Paule doth very wholsom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly instruct vs concerning this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wrytinge vnto the Romanes. Raunsoming the time bycause the dayes are euill. These wordes are few &amp; shortly spoken, and that they may be fully and perfectly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standed, they must thus be expound<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded. In the nature of the dayes,
<pb facs="tcp:176396:15"/> yf they be consydered alone and by them selues, there is no euell, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge they runne deuyded with a pleasant diuersyte, and carrye and recarrye into the worlde darknes and lyght, the one to followe the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in most goodlie ordre. But the Apostle calleth them euell, bycause that in their tyme. ii. greate euels chaunce vnto men, I meane mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye and synne. Howe myserable a lyfe we lyne in this worlde, thys playnlye proueth, that no parte therof is withoute mysery. When are we not other troubled or tēp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the nedes of nature? In what parte of our age is not oure lyfe layed in wayte for, other of dyseases, of outwarde chaunces, or noughtye men for to destroye vs? How innumerable are y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers which do besege vs on euery side? Graūt that al thīges be now and than quiet, who is out of the
<pb facs="tcp:176396:15"/> danger of false brethren? fynallye, who is he that professeth Christe, and is not greued, troubled, and miserablie vexed in his mynde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> his owne synnes or other mens? All these thynges withoute doubte do heape vp the myserie of our dayes. Sin also groweth, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaseth &amp; goeth forwarde more and more the longer that we lyue, vnles it be resysted, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> great hede and diligence. For our nature is so infected and corrupted with oure naturall dysease whiche they cal original synne y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we carrye aboute vs euen within our selues the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynninge and fountanie of al syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, whiche yf a man do diligently marke he shall perceaue that the Apostle hath truly writen y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes dwelleth not in oure fleshe. Out of this naturall corruption procede alwayes frowarde enten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, violente fumes, &amp; appetites in
<pb facs="tcp:176396:16"/> manner vnable to be vanquished, that striue against the law of god, whiche (alas) oftentimes (suche is oure weakenes) oure will (whiche should stoutely kepe them vnder) vnhappely obeyeth vnto. Yea (and y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> more pitie is) it is so established in thē by custome &amp; vse, that euery day it waxeth harder to heale than other. Therefore seinge our dayes are so euil, both by reason of mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye &amp; also of sinne, by abundaunte wealth, great authority, hie honor, men become neuer the better, but waxe y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prouder therby. He that ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth a commune weale though he haue hie dignitie, yet oftentimes lacketh he good health. For of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual cares &amp; troubles of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> minde, brede euyll humors in the bodye, whervpon cometh plenty of disea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses. As for outwarde perilles and chaūces y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> come by hap rūne moste abrod there wher they find metest
<pb facs="tcp:176396:16"/> &amp; largest rome. Wher (I pray you) do the blastes of enuy, the waues of wrath, the heat of hatred &amp; eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie more cruelly rage thā there. Manye times rise vp vaine peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and destruction prepareth it<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>self an easy way to crepe in, by our familiars, euen those whome we take to be our moste faithfull &amp; se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret frēdes. I speake nothing how greuously the minde is tourmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, when wise rulers do perceaue y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> oftentimes in the gouernance of the commune weale, those faultes which they or other do comit, can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not be redressed by theyr power &amp; authorite. Is ther not also a great numbre of miseryes heaped vp to encrease all these thynges whiche they must nedes suffre that rule in the cōmune weale? And although all men lyue myserable dayes, yet they most miserable of all whome the people thynketh happye.
<pb facs="tcp:176396:17"/> But nowe let vs loke asyde to the wretched pestilence of vices, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you recken those which be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural vnto vs, or passions that vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentlye burste out, or euell workes which are purposed &amp; agreed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, or noughtye customes and aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient vses, &amp; we shal sone perceaue, that men that be aduaunced to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable estate, haue lesse leysure to fyght against them than priuat mē haue. For whyle all the senses of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mynde are occupyed aboute com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune and other mens affaires, O Lorde, what darknes? how great a mist, kepeth them frō seyng their owne? In no state we knowe oure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selues worse than in that, and all our laboure tendeth to this ende, rather to make others better, than to fashion oure owne affections, workes and customes of our min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des accordynge to the law of God and heauenly doctryne. Therfore
<pb facs="tcp:176396:17"/> on both sydes y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> state of them that rule &amp; gouerne realmes, is vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier thā theirs which liue a priuat &amp; their owne life. For they are loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> heauier burdē of mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, &amp; abyde greater occasions of vices, &amp; they can least labour to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēde them selues. Wherfore God almyghtye somtyme pityeth their case, and fyndeth meanes for them to raunsome the dayes that be so e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell. But vnles we geue somwhat for to receaue somwhat agayne, it is no raunsominge. For we vse to call them raunsomed, which being bonde to some necessite paye som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what els to obteyne their lyberte. There to auoyde euels we must be contente to suffre some losse. Wyse and thriftie men do prouyde to put away the lesse good for to obteyne the greater, and take vpon thē the lesser euell for to auoyde the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. This doeth the worde raun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some
<pb facs="tcp:176396:18"/> signifye in oure commune speache. Thus cōmeth it to passe, that that is rather to be reioysed at, which blynde loue complayneth of in the fleshe. Therfore yf it at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tyme lament the losse of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite you had before, of the ordering of the commune weale, of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernaunce of the realme, and other lyke, let God be thanked whiche hathe partlye geuen you a raunso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge of the euell dayes. Therfore I saye, partlye, because whyle we are in this lyfe, they shall neuer be perfectlye good, but we saye that they haue raunsomed them that for some losse haue obteyned to haue them not so euell as they were. I haue red that it is a commune pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe among the people of Affrike. The plague standeth at thy dore to begge a pennye of the, geue him two to get him awaye. Surelye godly men ought to spende awaye
<pb facs="tcp:176396:18"/> muche ryches, speciallye suche as the ignoraunt people dothe moste esteme, for to obteine more greater soūde and certayne riches. We are wonte to recouer oure healthe by lettynge of bloude, often times we put awaye by coarsynge certayne pushes or painfull botches in oure bodye, partlye with cuttyng, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye with searinge, partlye w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge away parte of the membre. Why shoulde we not also be contēt to coarse the miserye of our lyfe, &amp; more pure affection of oure mynde with some losse. It is like to happē that they whiche do not here raun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some the euell dayes with putting awaye the commoditees of thys lyfe, and pleasures of the bodye, at the last daye of iudgemēt, they shal haue them worse, and that not for a shorte tyme, but for euer. And the wretches shal abye their folishnes, that caused them to set more by the
<pb facs="tcp:176396:19"/> lesse good than the greater. This we oughte surely to beleue y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> God our father dothe order al these thī<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. And yf we that be euell, can geue good giftes vnto our childrē, howe muche more shal our heauēly father prouide wel for his childrē? He taketh away somtimes earthly riches and worldly glory, that we maye learne the frailtye therof. Are we so folyshe, that (although we do see harde stones broken in processe of tyme) &amp; buildinges set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and strongly ioyned with lime, iron and led at length to decay, yet we thinke that good fortune and prosperite of this world wil abide for euer? With whiche errour we being led (somtymes farre frō the treuth) do set more by these goods which brute bestes haue as wel as we, and euell menne as wel as the good, than those which the lord of hys goodnes hathe appointed for
<pb facs="tcp:176396:19"/> hys chosen bothe in this life and in the worlde to come. And yet I do not write this vnto youre grace (most excellent Duke) as thoughe you had not these remedies and far better thē these in stoare. For I do wel knowe what knowledge &amp; wisdome y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> spirit of Christ hath ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen you, but that you shoulde take some pleasure in reding these, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideringe that throughe the selfe same spirit of Christ, concerning y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> selfe same thinges, all they that sauer of Christe agree in one selfe same tale, and thereby you maye be the more encouraged to vse thē. I wyshe youre grace in the lorde wel to fare, and offer vnto you (as I am no lesse bound both by your loue and benefites) my selfe and my seruice redye at al assayes.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your graces most humble Peter Martyr.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:176396:20"/>
            <q>Seke peace and ensue it. <bibl>Psal. xxxiii. i. Pet. iii.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>bookseller's device of Walter Lynne (McKerrow 103): "A ram marked with a W and a goat marked with an L."</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <q>The feare of the lord is the begin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge of wisedome
<bibl>Psalm. cxi. b. prou. ix. b. Iob. xxviii. Eccle. i. c.</bibl>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:176396:20"/>
            <p> ¶ Imprynted at Londō for Gaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Lynne, dwellynge on So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers Kaye, by Byl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynges gate.</p>
            <p>In the yeare of our Lorde M. D. L.</p>
            <p>¶ And they be to be solde in Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les churche yarde, nexte the great Schole, at the sygne of the sprede Egle.</p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio ad imprimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum solum.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>